Finding aid for the Paul Monette papers, 1945-1995 LSC.1707
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 1: Journals, 1971-1992
  - Journal Three, 23 Februrary 1974-13 May 1975; 300 pages; 20 x 25 cm (Box 58, Folder 5)
    Throughout the third journal, Monette discusses works of literature as he reads them. Virginia Wolfe's diaries, the first two volumes of Proust's In Search of Lost Time, Robert Frost's poems, and W. B. Yeats' poems feature most prominently. Often recopying long passages from texts he finds noteworthy, Monette expresses a particular affinity in the third journal for Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance. On a few occasions, Monette develops his thoughts on the literature he teaches at Milton. On pages 158 through 161 of the journal, for instance, Monette passionately explicates Frankenstein. Explicitly identifying himself with the monster, Monette adds that Frankenstein "is a terribly moving book, terribly rich" and that "one wants so much for Victor and his monster to love each other" (underlined in the original).
    The third journal also contains a few noteworthy features. Taped to the inside of the journal's front cover is a photograph of Monette from Sea Island as well as a roundtrip ticket for a boat ride from Boston to Provincetown. A map of Walden and its surrounding areas issued by the "Thoreau Lyceum" (which Monette describes on page 260 of the journal) is taped onto the back flyleaf. Finally, taped to the inside of the back cover is a photograph of Monette, in which he appears nude and standing in a shallow swimming hole beside a waterfall.
  - Journal Four, 15 May 1975-12 August 1977; 287 pages; 20.5 x 26.5 cm (Box 58, Folder 6-7)
    In the fourth of his thirteen journals, dating from May 15, 1975 to August 12, 1977, Paul Monette records his thoughts on his evolving relationship with Roger Horwitz and his writing career.
    The fourth journal begins with Monette and Roger (also referred to as "Rog" or "R") moving into separate apartments. Soon thereafter, however, they move in together. Throughout, the journal chronicles vacations the two take together to Maine, Florida, Provincetown, Chicago, Paris, Washington, D.C., and California. In California, they travel down the coast from San Francisco to Sand Diego, stopping at many locales along the way, including Big Sur, Carmel, Hearst's Castle, Los Angeles, and Laguna Beach. During these years, Monette expresses the desire to move to Los Angeles even though the idea of such a move causes, as he notes, him and Roger to worry over the longevity of their relationship. Referring to his "cruising" on the Boston Esplanade and at the community gym, Monette comments on Roger's occasional bouts of jealousy over what he refers to as Monette's "flings." Nevertheless, Monette regularly communicates a strong affection for Roger, especially when he and Roger are apart. Occasionally seeing a therapist of his own (Rick Friswell, or "RF"), Monette registers his concerns over Roger's therapy and psychoanalysis. Toward the end of the journal, Monette details a second and longer trip he takes alone to LA in order to promote his writing career and assess his feelings about moving there, with or without Roger. While there, he stays, for the most part, at the Bel Air home of Roger's half-brother Sheldon Andelson. Throughout the journal, Monette records worrying over moments of ill health, jots down notes on academic lectures, discusses meeting celebrities who he considers personal heroes (such as Joan Didion and Joan Baez), and explores his feelings when rereading portions of his previous journals. In addition, Monette scatters throughout the journal quotations from various authors, including Walt Whitman, Jane Austen, and Hunter S. Thompson.
    During this period, Monette describes a variety of occasions he spends with friends and family. Passing most of his time with dear friends Cesar and Craig, Monette additionally recounts visiting with Shannon (also "RFS"), Star Black, Rudy, Andy ("AR"), the couple John and Roger, Julia Cameron (his ex-girlfriend, who marries in this period Martin Scorsese), David Schorr, Sanford Friedman, Richard Howard, James Merrill, David Kalstone, and J.D. McClatchy (who begins dating poet and critic Alfred Corn in this period). Periodically, Monette notes visiting, as well, Gertrude Macy (or, "Gert") at Martha's Vineyard and Sneden's Landing. He writes about Gert in his later book of essays Last Watch of the Night: Essays Too Personal and Otherwise (1994), a fact that might explain why many of the pages in the journal where she appears are dog-eared. In a few entries, Monette discusses the marriage of his brother, Bob, to longtime girlfriend, Brenda. In one of these entries, Monette—uncharacteristically—prays: "Oh, please bless them, any odd god around, they are so innocent" (page 48 of the journal). Monette frequently mentions his mother's mounting curiosity in regards to Roger. His mother seems—Monette writes—"to ask in every sentence—why don't you tell me you're gay?" (page 142).
    As his writing career begins to thrive, Monette occasionally remarks on his growing comfort with the idea of being a writer. He mentions composing many of the poems that would eventually find their way into his second collection (No Witnesses [1981]), two screenplays (the first of which is titled Lovers and Dancers) with his friend John (of John and Roger, or "JK"), and an untitled television script. As the fourth journal documents, Monette also receives a writing fellowship from Harry Ford for five-thousand dollars, takes a year off from teaching at Milton Academy, teaches two graduate literature courses at Clark University, writes his first novel, Taking Care of Mrs. Carroll (1978), begins writing his second, The Gold Diggers (1979), and acquires a literary agent, Wendy Weil, who sells his first novel to Roger Donald at Little, Brown, and Company. On occasion, Monette notes when publications, such as Poetry or Christopher Street, accept his poems for print.
    The fourth journal contains a number of notable features. It includes a photograph of Monette taped inside the front cover, a photograph of Monette taped inside the back cover, a hand-written calendar on a piece of lined loose-leaf paper tucked between pages 108 and 109, a piece of adhesive tape on the edge of the back cover where Monette tried to repair a torn edge (see page 166), a letter by Cesar to Monette written on pages 263 and 264 directly, and what seems to be an autograph from Bette Davis (page 243). In addition, Monette cataloged the books he read during this period on the final two pages of the journal.
  - Journal Five, 13 August 1977-15 November 1979; 144 pages; 20.5 x 26.5 cm (Box 58, Folder 8)
    In the fifth of his thirteen journals, dating from August 13, 1977 to November 15, 1979, Paul Monette records his thoughts on moving to Los Angeles, his career, and his increasingly busy schedule.
    Sporadically kept, the fifth journal begins by chronicling Monette and his partner Roger Horwitz's trip to London. Soon thereafter, when Roger secures a new job as a lawyer with a West Coast development firm, the journal shifts its focus to their impending move to Los Angeles. Eventually buying a home on Kings Road in Hollywood (now West Hollywood), where he and Roger lived out the rest of their lives, Monette records his initial excitement over the canyon neighborhood of Beverly Glen. They rent a house there for a year. Throughout the journal, Monette details multiple trips back east to Boston, New Haven, and New York City as well as a vacation he takes with Roger to Hawaii. As the journal records, the couple celebrate their fourth and fifth anniversaries, respectively, by camping on the California-Oregon border and by renting cabins at Big Sur. During these years, Monette mentions "cruising" at public parks and abandoned docks as well as attending adult movie houses. The journal twice records Monette and Roger going to the doctor to be treated for gonorrhea. Monette frequently refers to using "dope" and, on occasion, cocaine (or, as he sometimes calls it, "tooting"). The fifth journal also notes that Monette's parents and brother begin treating Roger "like family." The journal chronicles his parents' visits out west to see him, his parents' and brother's financial difficulties, a discussion he and his parents have about his novels' gay subject matter, and a few occasions he and Roger spend with Roger's parents, Al and Bea (referred to as the "in-laws").
    For the most part, however, the fifth journal conveys a sense of Monette's increasingly hectic and demanding schedule as well as his desire to shift his creative focus from poetry to novels and screenplays. During this period, Monette describes working on multiple writing projects, sometimes jotting down notes on their themes and plots within the journal. As his first novel Taking Care of Mrs. Carroll (1978) appears in print, receiving mostly positive reviews, Monette discusses writing and selling, with the help of his agent Wendy Weil, his second novel, Gold Diggers (1979), to Robert ("Bob") Wyatt at Avon Books. He mentions writing and revising his third novel, The Long Shot (1981) and novelizing, under contract to Universal Pictures, Werner Herzog's Nosferatu. Monette recounts partnering with an associate named Renee to write three screenplays. They do so under the direction of producer Howard Rosenman and Universal executive Thom Mount. They title the first two screenplays No Contest and Time Out. The third remains unnamed and incomplete by the fifth journal's end. Throughout, Monette discusses the ins and outs of Rosenman's negotiations with actors—such as Jill Clayburgh, Christopher Walken, and Peter Bogdonavich—to star in No Contest. In addition, Monette records traveling with Renee (as well as Roger) to Philadelphia to observe a court case as research for a screenplay.
    The fifth journal documents, as well, Monette's increasing savoir-faire with the entertainment and publishing industries. Mingling with gay literary elite, such as Gore Vidal, Edmund White, and Christopher Isherwood (who refuses to endorse Monette's first novel), Monette frequently notes interviewing with the "gay press." Monette documents circulating in the entertainment industry as well, sighting and meeting celebrities such as LeVar Burton, John Wayne, Angie Dickenson, Robert De Niro, and John Brahm. Due to the influx of money from his various writing projects, Monette buys a Datsun and White Mercedes. The success also bolsters, maybe even inflates, Monette's sense of confidence, leading him to declare in one entry that no one is "ahead" of him as a writer, adding, "I mean it" (page 109).
    The fifth journal includes some notable features. There are two photos of Monette wearing the same outfit and most likely taken during his and Roger's trip to London taped in the journal, one inside the front cover and one inside the back. A clipping that reads "The Beale house in Grey Gardens" is taped to the inside of the journal's front cover as well. Also taped inside the back cover is a photograph of what seems to be the backyard of Monette and Roger's home on Kings Road. Inside the journal is John Brahm's autograph (page 68) and diagrams of his and Roger's cabins at Big Sur river (pages 133 and 134). In the back of the journal, Monette catalogs the books he reads as well as registers some terse one-word reviews, such as "Shit" and "Marvelous."
  - Journal Six, 18 November 1979-28 September 1982; 300 pages; 20 x 25 cm (Box 59, Folder 1-2)
    In the sixth of his thirteen journals, dating from November 18, 1979 to September 28, 1982, Paul Monette primarily registers his thoughts on his evolving relationship with Roger Horwitz, his love affair with Louis Weisberg, and his writing career.
    The sixth journal begins by recording a series of vacations Monette and Roger (also referred to as "Rog" and "R") take to New York City, Napa Valley, San Francisco, and France. Monette notes that while in Paris they meet, by happenstance, Andy Warhol, who, having heard of Monette's second novel, The Gold Diggers (1979), takes a photograph of the couple. Monette observes throughout the journal that, despite this noteworthy recognition, his most recent novel sells poorly and receives poor reviews, shaking his confidence and the outlook for his career. Despite selling his third novel, The Long Shot (1981), to Avon, Monette worries over the "near silence" that greets it (page 90 of the journal). As a result, Monette struggles, as the sixth journal records, to complete his fourth novel manuscript, Lightfall. The sixth journal conveys as well a sense of growing uncertainty surrounding Monette's screenwriting career, which his writing partner Renee declares—as the journal reports it—"over for the moment" (page 191). Monette recurrently attributes this dire outcome to an ongoing entertainment industry strike. Hired by a billionaire from Texas, Francois de Menil, Monette adapts the book Nothing But the Truth and the novel The Hamptons into screenplays, receiving up to a hundred thousand dollars for the latter project. Monette mentions traveling to the Hamptons to conduct research for this project, where he stays at one of David Geffen's homes and socializes with Lorne Michaels and Paul Simon. During this period, Monette also briefly mentions working on screenwriting projects called "Perfect Strangers" and "In a Lovely Place" and on a novel about Hawaii, as well as acquiring an additional agent named Lorraine (he retains his original agent, Wendy Weil).
    The majority of the sixth journal, however, documents Monette's sudden and passionate affair with a young hustler named Louis (also "L"). Monette even jots and revises an unpublished poem about Louis (page 102). Self-reflective about the fact that his passion for the young man might in fact be interrelated to his faltering writing career and perennial psychological concerns, Monette periodically relates the turbulence of these years to the turbulence of those recorded in his first two journals. At this time, Monette begins writing down notes from his therapy sessions with Sam Dubreville—a pattern that continues throughout all of his subsequent journals. These notes frequently delve into the links between Monette's fear of death, his personal guilt surrounding his brother's disabilities, his feelings of having missed out on his sexual adolescence, his growing boredom with Roger, and his desire to be more masculine and less "passive." The notes from these sessions also link Monette's feelings about Louis' hustling to his screenwriting career, which he describes as literary "prostitution." Frequently, as he weighs the pros and cons of his relationship with Roger and what he frequently calls his "obsession" with Louis, Monette's entries grow fragmented and sprawling, featuring arrows, flowcharts, emphatic underlines, and an excess of brackets. Monette takes note of his friends' input on the topic; more often than not, Michael Grace, writer J. D. McClatchy, David Schorr, and poet Charles Wright point out Louis' shortcomings. As he explores a renewed and explicitly-described sexual fervor and jots down the names of those he encounters sexually, Monette remarks that Roger has grown "sick of the whoring and the affairs" (page 279). The journal reports that Roger debates leaving the practice of law to become a writer as well. Monette additionally discusses nurturing Louis's ambition to write a play, a situation that inspires Monette, in turn, to write two plays of his own: "Just the Summers" and "Seven Point Two." Throughout this period, Monette comments on his mother's declining health and his parents' visits to Los Angeles. The journal comes to a close with Monette imaginatively addressing Louis, his therapist, Roger, McClatchy, and himself, advising each of them (including himself) on how each should behave going forward. The final journal entry mentions, as well, Monette's new, if short-lived, love interest—a man named Arthur.
    Monette's first reference to what would become the AIDS crisis occurs two-thirds of the way through the sixth journal: "The horror of the sickness. The visit to the doctor's. The fissure. The gay cancer scare. The poppers. Sense of grunginess. The sewage running down the street outside" (217, original underlining). A few other notable features occur as well. Tucked between pages 2 and 3 of the journal is a handwritten schedule of a trip to Greece and London (taken, so it seems, during a later period). Wedged between pages 140 to 141 is a greeting card bearing no signature (though most likely from Roger). Monette sketches his hotel rooms in France as well as views from their windows on pages 18, 19, 23, and 24. In the margin of page 61, Monette notes that an entry from "1/13[/81] is on a folded page in the flyleaf" but no such page has been found. A chronological and annotated list of books Monette read during this period—including his first two novels (the second of which, he comments, "seemed wonderfully whole, if a bit hard on the reader" [296])—can be found on the journal's final pages. Also, the journal's chronological flow is interrupted toward its end by notes Monette haphazardly scrawls while writing his plays.
  - Journal Seven, 9 October 1982-23 August 1983; 150 pages; 21 x 27 cm (Box 59, Folder 3-4)
    In the seventh of his thirteen journals, dating from October 9, 1982 to August 23, 1983, Paul Monette documents the process of writing a number of screenplays as well as his frequently troubled thoughts on his relationship with Roger Horwitz.
    Diverging from earlier journals, the seventh journal mostly functions for Monette as a notebook wherein he brainstorms ideas for his writing projects. Throughout this period, Monette mostly focuses on writing and refining, in collaboration with producers Howard Rosenman, Lindsay Doran, Allan Stewart, and Jeff Young, and in association with Norman Lear and Avco Embassy Pictures, a screenplay entitled 15 Minutes about a young woman who reluctantly becomes a model and a star. The screenplay additionally features two drag queens, a young chemist, and a fashion designer. However, the seventh journal depicts Monette working on a number of screenplays, novels, and plays. Working with the same affiliates, as well as several others, Monette develops treatments for a romantic comedy that he roots in Greek mythology, at first called "Wildwood" and then titled "Winter Spring," in which a love triangle springs up between a modern day mortal man (who becomes enchanted and begins to age backwards), a nymph, and a faun. By the end of the journal, Monette reworks the treatment into a plot for a novel. Monette outlines what seems to be a television series called "American Maid" in which three aspiring actresses live in the same building and even sketches the floor plan of their imagined building on page 107 of the journal. He briefly mentions two unspecified projects called "Sister" and "Gift Wrapped" and two novel ideas (one that would take place in Hawaii and the other in Laguna Beach). He occasionally comments on writing, revising, and publishing a novelization of the movie Scarface as well. Throughout this period, Monette notes revising his first play Just the Summers extensively and editing his second play Seven Point Two to a lesser extent. Throughout the course of the seventh journal, Monette relates the interest several stage producers—Robert Levithan and Barry Krost in particular—express in regards to his first play. Monette takes notes in his journal on rehearsals Krost mounts of Just the Summers in New York City. Throughout, Monette remarks on meeting with executives at Paramount, such as, most notably, Jeffrey Katenzberg.
    Intermittently, Monette discusses his personal life. Most of these entries are comprised of notes Monette takes at therapy sessions with Sam Dubreville. These entries frequently focus on Monette's struggle to find a balance between his sexual fantasies, his sexual encounters, and his relationship with Roger (also referred to as "Rog" and "R"). While it commences with Monette describing the painful closure of his brief affair with a man named Arthur, Monette discusses throughout the journal his recurrent and powerful feelings over a hustler named Louis Weisberg (also "L"). Near the end of the journal, Monette recounts a particularly painful period for him when Louis begins to cheat on his partner Michael with a man named Gene, a situation that awakens in Monette feelings of envy and sexual inadequacy. The sixth journal records friction that develops between Monette and his friends J. D. McClatchy and Alfred Corn over their differing views on questions of literary aesthetics. Monette occasionally mentions sleeping with a man named Stuart and reminds himself to be more attentive to Roger's needs. The couple takes trips, the journal reports, to Big Sur and Yosemite. Also, it should be noted, Monette becomes increasingly aware of the AIDS epidemic in this period. Using the word "AIDS" for the first time on page 82 of the journal, he writes, "How does one live sexually in the AIDS world?" A handful of long entries feature Monette thinking through strategies for how he might avoid acquiring the syndrome. In one entry, the thought of AIDS leads Monette to ruminate on the topics of loneliness and mortality. Periodically, Monette mentions visiting with his longtime friend Star Black as well as reading drafts of her poems.
    Monette wrote a large portion of the seventh journal out of order. The last third of the journal jumps between the summer and fall of '83 as well as the fall and winter of '82 and '83. Additionally, scribbled inside the front and back covers as well as on the front and back flyleaves are notes on 15 Minutes. Tucked between pages 68 and 69 is the program to a production of The Tempest sponsored by the 1984 Olympic Arts Festival. On occasion, phone numbers are jotted down in what appear to be hands other than Monette's (on page 48, for instance, Jennifer Lee, Richard Pryor's wife, has written her number, adding, "I think you are wonderful!"). An annotated list of books appears on the journal's final few pages. Eerily anticipating his imminent return to poetry in the AIDS era, Monette remarks in this catalog, after reading Simpson's Poets in Their Youth (1982), "Oh I'm so glad I'm not a poet" (page 149). He adds that poets are "sniveling types" who complain "about not enough time" (page 149).
  - Journal Eight, 11 December 1983-3 February 1985; 152 pages; 20.5 x 26.5 cm (Box 59, Folder 5)
    In the eighth of his thirteen journals, dating from December 11, 1983 to February 3, 1985, Paul Monette primarily jots down notes about his writing projects. Occasionally, as the AIDS crisis begins to touch him personally, he records his thoughts on mortality.